<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A proclamation commanding all Jesuites and popish priests to depart this kingdom</title>
            <author>England and Wales. Sovereign (1660-1685 : Charles II)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1663</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 5 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 3 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A32366</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C3235</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R15075</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12279585</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12279585</idno>
            <idno type="VID">58639</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A32366)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 58639)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 863:36)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A proclamation commanding all Jesuites and popish priests to depart this kingdom</title>
                  <author>England and Wales. Sovereign (1660-1685 : Charles II)</author>
                  <author>Charles II, King of England, 1630-1685.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>2 leaves.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by John Bill and Christopher Barker ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1663.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Cambridge University Library.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>At head of title: By the King.</note>
                  <note>At end of text: Given at our court at White-Hall, the ninth day of April, in the year of our Lord 1663. And of our reign the fifteenth.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Jesuits --  Great Britain.</term>
               <term>Catholics --  Great Britain --  Legal status, laws, etc.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="proclamation">
            <pb facs="tcp:58639:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 55 -->
            <head>
               <figure>
                  <head>C R</head>
                  <q>DIEV ET MON DROIT</q>
                  <q>HONI SOIT QVI MAL Y PENSE</q>
                  <figDesc>royal blazon or coat of arms</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </head>
            <head>By the King.</head>
            <head type="sub">A PROCLAMATION COMMANDING All Jeſuites and Popiſh Prieſts To depart this <hi>KINGDOM.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <signed>CHARLES R.</signed>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hereas Our Loyal Subjects the Lords and Commons in this preſent Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament aſſembled, by their humble Petition have repreſented to Vs, That notwithſtanding Our unqueſtionable Affection and Zeal to the true Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Religion, manifeſted in Our conſtant Profeſſion and Practice, againſt all Temptations whatſoever; Yet by the great reſort of Ieſuites and Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh Prieſts into this Kingdom, Our good Subjects generally were much affected with Iealouſie and Apprehenſion, that the Popiſh Religion might much increaſe in this Kingdom (Which We have moſt piouſly deſired may be prevented) and ſo the Peace both in Church and State may be inſenſibly diſturbed, to the great danger of both. The two Houſes of Parliament were therefore humble Suitors to Vs to iſſue out Our Proclamation to command all Ieſuites, and all Engliſh, Iriſh, and Scotiſh Prieſts, and all ſuch other Prieſts as have taken Orders from the See of <hi>Rome,</hi> or by Authority thereof (except ſuch forreign Ieſuites or Prieſts as by Contract of Marriage are to attend the Perſons of either of the Queéns, or by the Laws of Nations to attend forreign Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadors) to depart this Kingdom by a day, under pain of having the penalties of the Laws inflicted upon them. And We having ſeriouſly conſidered and weighed the ſaid humble Repreſentation and Petition of Our ſaid Lords and Commons aſſembled in Parliament, and the great Affection and
<pb facs="tcp:58639:2"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 56 -->
Duty with which the ſame was preſented unto Vs, and accepting with much contentment their great care for the preſervation of the true Religion eſtabliſhed in this Kingdom; Have therefore re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to publiſh this Our Admonition and Commandment, and do hereby require, charge, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand all Ieſuites, and all Engliſh, Iriſh, and Scotiſh Prieſts, and all ſuch other Prieſts as have taken Orders from the See of <hi>Rome,</hi> or by the Authority or pretended Authority thereof, Who are not under any reſtraint by Impriſonment, That they do before the fourteenth day of <hi>May</hi> next depart out of this Our Kingdom of <hi>England</hi> and Dominion of <hi>Wales,</hi> upon pain of having the Penalties of Our ſaid Laws inflicted upon them. And for their better means to depart accordingly, We do hereby Declare and Publiſh Our further Pleaſure, That if at any time before the ſaid fourteenth day of <hi>May</hi> next, they or any of them ſhall reſort to any Port-Town of Our ſaid Kingdom of <hi>England</hi> or Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion of <hi>Wales,</hi> and there declare himſelf to the Magiſtrate of the Town, or other Officers of any Port, that he is a Prieſt, and that he is there to take Shipping for his paſſage, they ſhall ſuffer him or them quietly to depart, and ſhall ſee them ſhipt and ſent away for forreign Parts, and give them their furtherance for their departure. And to the end this Our Proclamation may be the better obſerved and obeyed, We do hereby ſtrictly charge and command all Our Lieutenants, Deputy-Lieutenants, Commiſſioners, Iuſtices of the Peace, Mayors, Sheriffs, Bayliffs, and all other Our Officers whatſoever, that they be circumſpect and vigilant each of them in their ſeveral charges from and after the ſaid fourteenth day of <hi>May,</hi> in ſearching for, and diſcovering all ſuch Ieſuites and Prieſts as aforeſaid, as ſhall preſume to remain in this Our Realm of <hi>England</hi> or Dominion of <hi>Wales,</hi> contrary to Our Laws, and Our Royal Pleaſure and Command herein declared. Provided always, and Our intention is (which We do hereby declare) That this Our Proclamation do not extend to Prieſts that do or ſhall from time to time attend upon the Perſons of Our Deareſt Conſort the Queen, or of the Queén Our Dear Mother, according to the Treaties of their ſeveral Marriages, the names of which Prieſts ſhall be ſet down and ſignified by them under their Great Seals reſpective<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and ſuch ſignification inrolled in Our Court of Kings-Bench. And becauſe there may be ſome Prieſts impriſoned within this Our Realm yet unknown to Vs, We do will and command all She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riffs, Bayliffs, and Keepers of Priſons, within twenty days after the publication of this Our Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamation, to advertiſe Our Privy Council, or ſome of them, of the names of all ſuch Prieſts that are in their Cuſtody, and by whom, and for what cauſe they were committed, to the end that thereupon We may give order for their Tranſportation, as the Caſe ſhall require.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Given at Our Court at <hi>White-Hall,</hi>
                  <date>the Ninth day of <hi>April,</hi> in the year of our Lord 1663. And of Our Reign the Fifteenth.</date>
               </dateline>
               <lb/>
GOD SAVE THE KING.</closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>John Bill</hi> and <hi>Christopher Barker,</hi> Printers to the Kings moſt Excellent MAJESTY, 1663.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:58639:3"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 57 -->
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
